Guide to Philosophy Talk SC1118
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Philosophy Talk
2002-2018
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Taylor, Kenneth Allen, 1954-
Perry, John, 1943-
Landy, Joshua
Satz, Debra
SC1118
43008 megabyte(s) (457 computer files)
2.25 Linear Feet 5 boxes
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
Philosophy Talk is a talk radio program co-hosted by Stanford professors John Perry and Ken Taylor. The program deals both with fundamental problems of philosophy and with the works of famous philosophers, especially as these relate to our contemporary, day-to-day lives. Some of the wide range of topics of past programs include terrorism, Bush's doctrine of pre-emptive self-defense, Descartes, genetic engineering, and virtue. The program airs from the studios of KALW, 91.7 FM, Information Radio, San Francisco, California, and is produced by Ben Manilla Productions, Inc. on behalf of Stanford University, as part of its Humanities Outreach Initiative.
The show focuses on one topic or famous philosopher for an hour at a time, with an invited guest who is an expert on the philosopher or area of philosophy in question. As with most philosophical discussions, each show usually provides some factual information about the topic, as well as methods and points of view that are helpful in thinking about the topic. The Philosophy Talk motto is, "the program that questions everything, except your intelligence."
Philosophy and aesthetics; Philosophy -- History; Philosophy; Taylor, Kenneth Allen, 1954-; Perry, John, 1943-; Landy, Joshua; Satz, Debra
- Program audio, 2002-2018
  - Pilot #1: Can Machines Think?, 2002 Jan 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Scope and Contents
    Will Computers someday be able to have humanlike consciousnes and intelligence? Will they someday outstrip the thinking of humans? Would it matter if they did? Or is Artificial Intelligence on fundamentally the wrong track?
  - Pilot #2: Terrorism, 2002 Jan 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What is terrorism? Is terrorism morally worse than other forms of warfare. Was Truman's decision to drop the A-bomb and act of terrorism? Is the US a terrorist State? Is terrorism an insult the powerful use to deligitimate the only means of resistance open to the disempowered?
  - Bush's Doctrine of Preemptive Self-Defense, 2004 Jan 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Scope and Contents note
    What is the difference between mere aggression and preemptive self defense? Can you really permissibly "defend" yourself against an attack that hasn't even begun? How does preemptive self defense differ from preventive war, from humanitarian intervention?
  - Would You Want to Live Forever?, 2004 Jan 20; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Pick your favorite age. You are healthy, career thriving, family intact (at least pretend!). Would you like to live forever at that age, in that health, with those friends and family members also living forever with you? Immortality, on earth? How about an extra fifty or one hundred years or two hundred beyond your present life expectancy?
  - Race, 2004 Jan 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is race a discredited pseudo-scientific category? Or a real dimension of difference among humans? Or a socially constructed reality? What difference does it make?
  - Marriage and the State, 2004 Feb 3; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    With what right does the state say who can and cannot marry? The state has, at various times, said that people of different races cannot marry, that people of the same sex cannot marry, that no one can marry more than one person at at time. But with what legitimate authority can the state make such prohibitions?
  - Patriotism versus Cosmopolitanism, 2004 Feb 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Patriotism versus Comopolitanism: Is your loyalty to America and Americans more important than the common humanity you share with everyone on the globe?
  - The Insanity Defense, 2004 Feb 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Ken and John debate (use?) the insanity defense. What difference does it make if the person who commits a crime is, in one way or another, mentally ill? Does this make punishment illegitimate? Why is punishment, rather than therapy, ever legitimate? Which sorts of mental illness should exempt a criminal from punishment? Inability to know right from wrong? Inability to resist compulsion? Irrational depravity?
  - Drug Legalization, 2004 Feb 24; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Ken and John discuss the philosophical issues underlying arguments for and against the legalization of drugs. Does America's drug problem rest on confused philosophy? Listen in and get more confused.
  - Genetic Engineering and Cloning, 2004 Mar 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Ken and John and Ken and John discuss cloning and the ethical issues surrounding genetic engineering. When is genetic manipulation morally permissible? For health? Beauty? Wit? What sorts of animals is it acceptable to clone? Should we ban stem cell research?
  - Markets and Morality, 2004 Mar 9; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Ken, John and Elizabeth Anderson take on the topic of markets and morality.Does the free market provide incentives for behavior that is problematic from a moral perspective?Or does the free market punish morally problematic behavior?Is respecting the free market itself moral, insofar as respecting the free market is also respecting individual freedom of choice?
  - Nietzsche, 2004 Mar 16; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Nietzsche. Ken and John and Ãœbermensch-at-large Brian Leiter discuss everyone's favorite syphilitic philosopher. Was he a mysogynistic Nazi-supporter, or an artistic visionary who sought to set us free from our moralistic chains? Boring radio is dead.
  - Has Science Replaced Religion?, 2004 Mar 23; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Has science replaced religion? Can one be religious and maintain a scientific viewpoint? Does belief in evolution undermine morality or belief in God, or vice versa? Ken and John take on the big questions.
  - Humor, 2004 Mar 30; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Ken, John and guest Ted Cohen, author of Jokes: Philosophical Thoughts on Joking Matters discuss the philosophical aspects of humor. What is humor? What makes some jokes funny? Why did the chicken cross the road? Tune in for deep thoughts and big laughs.
  - Consciousness, 2004 Apr 6; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is the conscious mind just the brain or something more? Can science explain consciousness? How does Ken know that John is a conscious being and not just an automaton programmed to act like a conscious being? Or is John just an automaton?Is the conscious mind just the brain or something more? Can science explain consciousness? How does Ken know that John is a conscious being and not just an automaton programmed to act like a conscious being? Or is John just an automaton?
  - Taxation, 2004 Apr 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    How is taxation different from stealing? What right does the government have to take some of our money? No taxation without representation? What difference does representation make?
  - Baseball, 2004 Apr 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What can we learn from baseball? Are the passions we have for our baseball teams and heroes irrational? If so, what makes passions for families, cities, countries, universities, or radio stations more rational? Are all allegiances and loyalties ultimately arbitrary? Eminent Kant scholar and baseball fan extraordinare Allen Wood visits.
  - Whose Language Is It?, 2004 May 4; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is there a right and a wrong way to speak English? Is there really something wrong with saying, "Hopefully, we'll have a good century?" or "Where is the library at?", or "There is no way to correctly split an infinitive." Is grammatical purity just snobbism?
  - Animal Rights, 2004 May 11; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We shouldn't be mean to animals. Is that because animals have rights, like people do? Or is it just because people care about animals? Is it intrinsically worse to step on dog than on a spider?
  - Meaning of Life, 2004 May 18; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Does life have a meaning? If we were created by a powerful God, would that give our lives meaning? Who gave God's existence meaning? What if we were created by a crazy scientist wholly for the purpose of irritating his or her spouse?
  - Terrorism, 2004 Jun 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We like to think that terrorism is always wrong. But what if the cause is just? Do the ends ever justify the means? And how do we define "terrorism" anyway?
  - Dignity and the End of Life, 2004 Jun 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Join John and Ken and their guest, Peggy Battin, as they discuss dignity and the end of life. Is physician assisted suicide morally okay? What about active euthanasia for patients suffering terminal illnesses? If we begin traveling down this path, how do we put a break to our slide down the slippery slope toward a world in which we license physicians to kill or assist the suicide of severely depressed but not terminally ill patients?
  - Virtue, 2004 Jun 15; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    What is virtue?Is virtue the key human happiness and flourishing, as the ancients held, or a quaint notion of at best secondary interest for ethics, as many modern theorists hold? Does the return of virtue ethics to the philosophical scene mark an advance in our thinking about morality or is it just a nostalgia for morally simpler times?
  - Humans: The Irrational Animal, 2004 Jun 29; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Some psychologists claim to have demonstrated that humans are systematically, deeply and perhaps irredeemably irrational in their reasoning and decision making. But what is rationality and why does it matter? If we are really so irrational, how have we managed to get this far as a species? Maybe rationality isn't such a big deal after all. Tune in as Ken Taylor and guest host Nadeem Hussain size up the human mind.
  - Paternalism and Health, 2004 Jul 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Paternalism and Health: Some diseases such as Alzheimer's inhibit our abilities to make decisions and lessen our quality of life. In cases like these, we often think that others are justified in stepping in and making decisions for that person. But what about the case where the person in question is relatively healthy but suffers, perhaps, from minor depression, or an anxiety disorder? When (if ever) is it OK to step in and take charge of someone else's life or body?
  - Who Owns Ideas?, 2004 Jul 20; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    You can own a car or a bicycle. But what about an idea? If you invent a program it seems like you should have some say about its use. But can you really own the idea itself? Listen in and steal an idea or two.
  - Affirmative Action, 2004 Aug 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is affirmative action a way of balancing out inequality? Or is it just another form of bias in admissions and hiring practices? And where's the line between fostering diversity and lowering standards?
  - Gambling, 2004 Aug 24; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Rolling the dice in a game you're rigged to lose sounds like a bad idea. So why is it so much fun? Is gambling an exciting pastime, or a vicious addiction?
  - Happiness, 2004 Aug 31; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is happiness a mere psychological state? And if so, what's so important about it? Is there anything more to being happy than just thinking you're happy? Or is happiness a way of life?
  - Plato, 2004 Sep 14; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    From his theory of the Forms, to his views about morality, justice, and the soul Plato was one the greatest and most influential philosophers of all time. Indeed, it has been said that all of philosophy is but a footnote to Plato. Find out why as John and Ken dig into the philosophical views of Plato, with their guest, Chris Bobonoich, a leading Plato scholar.
  - Corporations, 2004 Sep 21; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Corporations are recognized as persons in the eyes of the law. But if they are persons, they would seem to be pathologically self-interested persons, driven by nothing but the desire for their own further aggrandizement. How can we cope with such persons in our midst?
  - The Environment and Global Justice, 2004 Sep 28; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Our current way of life is unsustainable. Depletion of the ozone layer, the dwindling of the rain forest, the loss of animal habitat, and toxic runoff into lakes, streams and rivers are just a few of the environmental challenges we face. The environment is a global problem that no one nation can address on its own. Something must give, somewhere. But who will pay what costs for improving the global environment? Wealthy nations of the North? Developing nations of the South? By what principles of justice shall we decide?
  - Feminism, 2004 Oct 12; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Some feminists hold that there are specially feminine ways of knowing, and the current scientific research is flawed for not recognizing them. Some hold that philosophy itself is a thoroughly phallocentric enterprise, and deeply flawed. Other feminists vigorously reject these views. Join John and Ken as they discuss the philosophies of feminism.
  - Karl Marx, 2004 Oct 19; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The ideas of Karl Marx vie with those of Rousseau, Locke and Jefferson for shaping the politics of the twentieth century. Are Marx's ideas of real philosophical value and interest, or simply relics of interest only in trying to understand the benighted century we have left behind?
  - Is This Any Way to Run a Democracy?, 2004 Nov 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    America prides itself on being the oldest continuous democracy in the world. But criticisms of the America system are widespread.Our system is tailored to narrow interests and wealthyelites. Our two partieslock out alternative voices. Ourvoting procedures discourage participation and lead to unrepresentative outcomes. Is this really the best way to run a democracy? Join John and Ken as they examine the philosophicalunderpinnings of democracy in America.
  - Time, 2004 Nov 9; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Time is the most familiar thing in the world, and yet philosophically one of the most puzzling. Is the present what's left when you subtract what has already happened, and what is yet to happen? Then it seems to vanish into a mere instant.Are future events completely unreal? Or are they just the things we can't know yet? Is time unreal, as many philosophers have thought? Columbia's Dave Albert joins John and Ken for a fascinating hour.
  - Truth and Relativism, 2004 Nov 16; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is there such a thing as absolute truth, independent of who is doing the thinking, and where?Or is truth relative to backgrounds, cultures, creeds, times, and places?Can it be true that what is right for me isn't right for you? John and Ken search for truth with Helen Longino, Professor of Philosophy and Women's Studies at the University of Minnesota.
  - Love, 2004 Nov 30; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is love just a (second-hand) emotion? Is it a feeling? A disparate group of feelings, glandular responses, and ill-considered commitments condensed into a single word so that poets will have something to write about?A poor substitute for true friendship imposed upon us by lust? Or the deepest and most satisfying of human conditions?
  - Disability, 2004 Dec 7; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The Americans with Disabilities Act recognizes that people with disabilities are often prevented from leading productive and satisfying lives because social, school and work environments are often thoughtlessly and unnecessarily designed with only people with the standard set of abilities in mind. In manycases"reasonable accommodation" to the ways people with disabilities need to do things is required. What is reasonable? Elevators in schools? Probably. How about elevators in the Grand Canyon?What is a disability? Blindness? Certainly. How about obesity? Where do we draw lines, and on what principles?
  - Nature vs. Nurture, 2004 Dec 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    The philosopher John Locke thought we had no innate ideas; our minds are blank slates, upon which experience writes.Nurture is everything, nature nothing.Modern popular genetics gives the impression that we are nothing but the stage on which a play written by our genes is performed; nature is everything, nurture nothing.What are the facts, and what are the philosophical principles that are used to interpret these facts?
  - Gender, 2005 Jan 4; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Are gender roles and differences fixed, once and for, all by biology? Or is gender socially constructed and culturally variable? How does gender differ from sex? Join John and Ken as they explore whether men and women are really from different planets after all.
  - The Mystery of Mind, 2005 Jan 11; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Modern science tells us that the mind is just the brain working.But science cannot yet tell us how consciousness, rationality,free will, autonomy, or even our sense of self arises out of the merely material processes of the brain. Could our confidence that mind is just the brain working possibly be misplaced?
  - Aristotle, 2005 Jan 25; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Aristotle'sphilosophical doctrines have permeated and helped shape Western Culture in spheres as disparate as cosmology, biology, ethics, physics, politics, and logic.Join John and Ken for a tour of some of the greatest hits of one of the greatest philosophers ofAntiquity.
  - Evil, 2005 Feb 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Is there such a thing as pureevil in the world?How should we confront evil?Can evilever be finally overcome? If the universe was created by a supremely good, supremely powerful, supremely loving deity, why is there evil in the world to begin with? On the other hand, if there is no god and everything is permitted, what distinguishes the truly evil from the purely good?
  - Ethics in Sport, 2005 Feb 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Once upon a time,student athletes were students first, athletes second; the Olympics was about amateurism and the pursuit of excellence, not the pursuit ofendorsements; and professional athletes enhanced the physics through rigorous work-outs, not through performance enhancing substances.No doubt athletic excellence is at an all time high, but are ethics in athletics at an all time low?
  - The Erotic vs. The Pornographic, 2005 Feb 15; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Erotic experience is a human good. Mature, consenting adults should be able to explore the erotic realm freely, without outside interference.Pornography is illicit and destructive.But what is the real difference between the erotic and the pornographic?Is there a bright line?In our attempts to regulate pornography do we run the risk of infringing upon the erotic freedoms of consenting adults?
  - Hume, 2005 Mar 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    David Hume's was a superb essayist,a brilliant philosopher, and a world-class bon vivant. His philosophical viewsin ethics, epistemology, aesthetics, and the philosophy of religion, though shocking to many in his own time,are enduring touchstones of modern philosophy, still required reading of every student of philosophy. Join John and Ken for a tour of a few ofHume's most startling ideas.
  - Religion and the Secular State, 2005 Mar 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Can committed believers and committed non-believers share a common political life in the context of a secular state?Committed believers may want the policies of the stateto reflect their deeply heldreligious convictions and values.Committed non-believers may notwant the state imposing religiously inspired values in the absence of any purely secular justification.Must religion retreat from the public sphere or can religion find a place in the public sphere, even in a purely secular state?
  - What is Beauty?, 2005 Mar 15; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Are there objective standards of beauty? Or is beauty in the eye of the beholder?Must art be beautiful to be great art?What is the role of the experienceof beauty in a good life?
  - Neurocosmetology, 2005 Mar 22; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Progress in neuroscience may soon make possible an age of neurocosmetology: the use of drugs to let people affect the way their brains work, so as to make them more effective, more attractive, and more like their "cognitive ideal."A world where all the women are beautiful and all the men handsome might be bearable if boring. But would a society full of type-A's work at all?Can it be rational to choose to change in ways that may change who you are? Should there be moral or legal prohibitions against healthy people messing with their own brain chemistry?
  - Is Free Will an Illusion?, 2005 Mar 29; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    We like to think of ourselves as enjoying unrestricted freedom of the will.But modern science increasingly teaches us that our choices are causally determined by some combination of our genes, our upbringing, and our present circumstances.Can the idea of freedom of the will be reconciled with the scientific outlook or is free will an illusion?If we give up on the idea that we have freedom, what follows for our practice of holding people morally responsible for their actions and choices?
  - Schopenhauer, 2005 Apr 5; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Arthur Schopenhauer, the great Nineteenth Century philosopher, had a pessimistic vision of the world as "will and idea.  Our will to survive serves no high purpose; the world is at best a shared illusion. Schopenhauer influenced Nietzsche and Wittgenstein and inspired our guest, prominent psychiatrist Irv Yalom, to write the novel The Schopenhauer Cure. What truths, metaphysical or psychological, can we wrest from Schopenhauer's gloomy vision?
  - Genetic Determinism, 2005 Apr 19; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Are there genes for practically everything? For being gay? For being mean? For being a philosopher? Does modern science show that we are largely the product of our genes --- or not? Join Ken and John and famed philosopher of biology John Dupre to see how trapped you are by your genes.
  - Propaganda, 2005 Apr 26; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Allegedly independent radio commentators taking money to spout the government line! Fake news reports being produced and distributed by the Administration to promote a partisan agenda! Journalists abandoning neutrality and objectivity to become cheerleaders for a political doctrine! Where can this happen? Right here in the good old U.S. of A. propaganda is all around us! But what exactly is propaganda? How can it be distinguished from legitimate news and information? Can democracy survive where propaganda flourishes? Join John and Ken for a fresh, philosophical look at propaganda.
  - Forgiveness, 2005 May 3; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Justice is a virtue and so, many claim, is forgiveness. But they seem inconsistent. Is forgiveness really a virtue? Philosopher Charles Griswold discusses the South African reconciliation process, truly evil people, and the virtue of forgiveness.
  - Confucius, 2005 May 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)
    Confucius laid down a pattern of thinking followed by more people for more generations than any other human being on the face of the earth. No matter what religion, no matter what form of government, the Chinese (and most other East Asian civilizations) and their way of thinking can in some way be shown to have Confucian elements about them. Join John and Ken as they discuss the ancient wisdom of Confucius.
  - Prostitution, 2005 May 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp3)